hello this is Eric with two pieces of
housekeeping before we get to today's
episode with Sir Roger Penrose now in
the first place we released episode 19
on the biomedical implications of
Brett's evolutionary prediction from
first principles of elongated telomeres
in laboratory rodents I think it's a
significant enough episode and we've had
so much feedback around it
before we continue any kind of line of
thinking surrounding that episode we'll
wait for my brother and his wife Heather
huiying to return from the Amazon where
they're currently incommunicado
so thanks for all the feedback it's been
very interesting to process the second
piece of housekeeping surrounds today's
episode with Roger Penrose now I know
what I'm supposed to do I'm supposed to
talk about quantum consciousness and the
emperor's new mind maybe ask Roger about
the many-worlds interpretation of
quantum mechanics or the weirdness of
quantum entanglement I'm actually not
that interested I also don't want to go
back to his earliest work on
singularities and general relativity
with Stephen Hawking what I instead want
to do is to remind you what Roger is in
fact famous for he's one of the greatest
geometric physicists now living he's
perhaps the best descendent of Albert
Einstein currently still working in
theoretical physics in this particular
line of thought I also think he's a
great example of what the UK does well
he has a very idiosyncratic approach to
trying to solve the deepest problems in
theoretical physics called twister
theory I'm not expert in it and I can't
always follow it so if you're not
following everything in today's episode
instead of deciding that the episode has
somehow failed you try to remember that
people who are working in mathematics
and theoretical physics spend most of
their time listening to colleagues
completely lost as to what their
colleagues are saying so if you start to
feel that you are being left behind by
some line of thinking what we do is in
general wait to see if another line of
thinking opens up that we can try to
catch you're not going to get all of the
waves and in fact the same thing is
happening to me while I'm interviewing
Roger he's not understanding everything
I'm saying I'm not understanding
everything he's saying and in fact this
is normal so what I would like to do is
to instead present you guys with an idea
of what science actually sounds like
when people are talking from two
slightly different perspectives we spend
an awful lot of time simply trying to
understand each other and if that feels
a little bit uncomfortable
well then in fact you're getting a true
scientific experience which is often
very different than what you're getting
when everything is pre-chewed in
spoon-fed hope you enjoy it without
further ado Sir Roger Penrose hello you
found the portal I'm your host Eric
Weinstein and I'm here today with none
other than sir roger penrose roger
welcome good to have you I'm extremely
excited about having you here there are
lots of questions that you typically get
asked these days many of them about
consciousness some of them about art
objects that come out of your thinking
but I know you in a professional
capacity as one of the important most
important people at the Nexus of
geometry and physics in our time of
course you can't say that you can make
all sorts of faces but I can assure you
that it's true you know there's a
Leonard Cohen quote where from a song
called the future where he says you
don't know me from the wind you never
will you never did but I'm the little
Jew that wrote the Bible and I have what
I consider to be the Bible right here
which is a book you wrote called the
road to reality which there's no getting
away from maybe in my opinion the most
important modern book of our time
because what it tries to do is to
summarize what we know about the nature
of all of this at the deepest level and
I think what I want to do is to
introduce you to our audience which has
been habituated over perhaps 16 or so
interviews not to expect to understand
everything they want to work they want
to hear conversations unlike any they've
heard and so we'll do some combination
of explaining things but some
combination of allowing them to look up
things in their own free time if your
game should we talk about the road to
reality and you can talk about that
that'd be great
so we're where are we in the history of
coming to understand what this place is
in which we find ourselves what we are
made out of and what we know about our
own context it's a very tough question
that I mean
when I wrote that book it was more or
less the state of the world at the time
I now feel I should rewrite part of it
because things have changed in one
important way in particular as far as
I'm concerned whether other people agree
with me is another question but I don't
think I'm going to rewrite it because it
was such an effort and I don't think I
would be likely to live long enough to
do a good job out of it it has that much
really changed since you wrote the book
a lot of level a lot has not changed the
thing that has changed in my view he
sees whether people agree with me on
this is another question is to do with
cosmology right you see I have a
proposal which I didn't have I mean it's
new since the book it's not all that new
because it's about 15 years old but it's
new since I wrote that book in an art
time skills that's quite new now that's
pretty new let's just just to get some
context you were born in the early 1930s
yeah um yes okay you you got a chance to
live through if not the original general
relativistic and quantum revolutions
their consequences in particular you
were able to take classes from people
like Paul Dirac who scarcely seems like
a human being sometimes more like a god
oh yeah that was an experience yes yes
whether I when I was at Cambridge as a
graduate student I did my undergraduate
work at London University University
College and then I went to Cambridge as
a graduate student and I went to do
algebraic geometry so I wasn't trying to
do physics at all and I I'd encountered
a friend of my brothers dennis sciama
when i think i was at university college
isn't undergraduate and he given a
series of talks on cosmology but it
started with the the earth and then he
sort of worked his way out and then
talked about what was then referred to
as the steady state theory where the
galaxies the universe expands and
expands and expands but it doesn't
change because all the time there is new
matter created hydrogen and the universe
expands and then you get new material
and it keeps replenishing what's gets
lost and I thought it was quite an
intriguing I mean I Dennis was a great
fan of this model and so I was really
taken by it so that where the story was
that I was in Cambridge visiting my
brother my older brother Oliver who did
statistical mechanics and he was
actually much more precocious than I was
he was two years ahead and he was I
think finishing his research there but I
had been listening to these talks by
Fred Hoyle and he was talking I think in
his last talk about how in the steady
state model the galaxies expands it way
expands away and then when they reached
the speed of light they disappear and I
thought that can't be quite right and I
started drawing pictures with like cones
and things like this and I thought well
they would simple they would fade
gradually fade but they wouldn't just
disappear and when I visited Cambridge
visiting my brother and we were at this
the kingswood restaurant in Cambridge
and I said to my brother said look I
don't understand what Fred was saying he
doesn't sort of make sense to me and he
said but I don't know about cosmology
but sitting over there on the table is a
friend of mine he knows all the answers
to these things and that was Dennis
Sharma and so I explained this problem I
had to Dennis and he was pretty
impressed because he didn't he said he
didn't know the answer but he would ask
Fred Fred Hoyle and but the main thing
was that when I did come up to do
graduate work in djenne in algebraic
geometry Dennis decided to take me under
his wing and try to persuade me to
change my subject and do we're
simultaneously under the great geometers
Hodge as well as Dennis Trump
well Hodge was my supervisor
see Dennis was just a friend I said Haji
was my supervisor originally until he
threw me out and and Todd became my
supervisor that's another little story
but but Dennis just wanted to get me
interested do work in cosmology this was
it
I never he wanted me to change my
subject I learned an awful lot from
Dennis about physics because Dennis sort
of knew everything and everybody and he
had a real knack of getting if he
thought two people should meet each
other he got made sure they did meet
each other in one case it was Stephen
Hawking but Dennis was actually a hey
when you mentioned Iraq Dennis was
actually the last graduate with at the
time he was the only graduate student of
Dirac's is that right yes Dennis was mr.
art was famously sort of difficult I
think that you know in recent years this
book came out of grammar mail of the
strangest man that puts directs
bizarreness he was difficult to get to
know but there's a bit of an irony here
I mean certainly he was hard for
physicists and so on to get to know him
now there were two people and actually
maybe I could just say one thing to our
listeners yes
in my estimation if not yours Dirac
would be neck and neck with Einstein for
the greatest of 20th century physicists
I think I wouldn't be far off at that
description for some reason his press
wasn't nearly as good maybe because of
his hair I don't know
well he didn't talk much this is one of
the problems no I agree I think he was I
mean you think about all the quantum
mechanics people who developed that
amazing subject and Dirac was really the
one who put it all in order and so on
well is is is and this gets to a very
odd issue which is that you have wielded
taste and beauty as a weapon your entire
life your drawings are among the most
compelling I remember the first time one
of the things I've done
using our friend Joe Rogan's program is
to push out discussion of the hopf
fibration because it's an it's the only
non-trivial principle bundle that can be
visually seen mm-hmm and since the world
seems to be about principle bundles it's
a bit odd that the general population
doesn't know that stuff of which we are
yes we're like the hopf fibration or the
Clifford parallels was instrumental in
the subject of Krishna theory well but
the first time I ever saw a diagram it
was somebody reproducing a diagram they
had seen of yours and so the way in
which you have used art and sketches
moment yeah it was drawn by hand largely
I mean they were running some circles
involved which I use a compass for but
basically I drape my hand there were two
versions of it the first one was more I
sort of thread you die first one was had
more circles in it and I thought I draw
there's more simply in the second
version but actually I had three
versions the third version is in the
road to reality but I'm not sure it's
best I think the second version perhaps
is the best so so Dirac getting back to
it had this elegance of mind
it was unrelenting yes and he famously
brought in these bizarre objects with
which some of us are obsessed others of
us don't understand the obsession called
spinners which is whatever a
prerequisite to getting to twist your
theory which you've popularized well I
went to the UC Dirac gave a course of
lectures in quantum mechanics and the
first course was sort of basic quantum
mechanics and the second course was on
quantum field theory but also spinners
and there's an interesting story about
that which I don't know the answer to in
the second course he deviated from his
normal course of lectures now I
understood when I talked to Graham
farmer
who wrote this biography of Dirac I
understood from grand family that when I
described that Dirac deviated from his
normal course to give two or three
lectures on two component spinners which
for me were absolutely what I needed you
see I'd learned from my work on
algebraic geometry which ended that by
trying to understand tensor systems as
abstract systems and things which you
can't represent in terms of compare
should just say that in terms of these
two components spin as you're talking
out for the lay audience all of the
matter that they think about whether
it's in bound up in electrons or the
quarks that make up protons and neutrons
if you think of these things as waves
which many people in our audience will
be familiar with that concept the
question is what are they wait what
medium are they waves in and they're the
medium would be a medium of spinners
which is not something that's easy for
people to understand
yeah well it's they're not and certainly
the formalism you see Dennis I told him
I need to understand about spinners and
particularly to the simplest ones of
these two components - and he suggested
I read this book by Corson so I got the
book by course and and I found it
completely incomprehensible just the I
mean it was a fascinating book because
it it was very comprehensive and
described all these different spins
fields and different things like that
and using a lot of two components
minutes which is the right way to do it
but to introduce what these objects were
was almost incomprehensible I found
mainly because you have these
translation symbols all over the place
and they mess up the appearance of the
formula so I just found this thing very
complicated and incomprehensible but
then I went to Dirac's second course it
may have been not the same year I think
he went one year I did the first and
maybe the second course was when I was a
research fellow rather than when I was a
graduate student I can't quite remember
I think must have been when I was a
graduate research fellow
way he this was a course on quantum
field theory and things like that but he
sort of deviated from his normal course
in one week to talk about two components
minutes and fame for me this was exactly
what I needed it made the whole subject
clear from this complete confusion that
it had before now then you see many
years later I talked to Graham farmer
and I told him the story and he said
that's a very strange Dirac would never
deviate from his course he just he
thought when he got his course perfect
it was perfect he would never change and
this was true of his first yeah of
course the short term the initial course
which I went to which people often said
to me well I think it's not such a great
course it's exactly like his book well
hadn't read his book so to me this was
sure the book is amazing too but not
having read the book I found this course
absolutely stunning and it made things
after you think Dirac actually
understand understood these objects is
most mysterious of various Minnis
spinners in general I mean he brought
them into physics they had been
previously found inside of mathematics I
think by people like killing and Lee I'm
not sure yes but cotton is the car ten
perhaps I don't think I mean let me
throw out a really dangerous I yeah I
don't think any of us understand them at
all and the part of the problem was is
that he understood very well what could
be said about them yeah but that if you
know I asked you before but like your
favorite film you said 2001 you could
make an argument that spinners are in
mathematics and physics like the Monell
if it's always encountered nobody ever
understands exactly what it means but it
always grabs your attention because it
seems so absolutely bizarre and highly
conserved well I always like to think of
things geometrically and least for the
two component ones you see when you go
up to higher dimensions you still have
spinners but the spinners the dimension
of the spinners goes up exponentially so
each time you add the two to the
intervention of
space and the dimension of spinors is
multiplied by two so I think I mentioned
2d for example yeah you'd get spinners
of dimension 2 to the D over 2 that's
the sort of thing that's right and so
the the well the usually ones talks
about the dirac spinors which are the
four Dement the for the false means
right but they split into these two two
and two
in even dimensions yes that's right in
even dimensions and I like to understand
these things geometrically so you could
see what the two-component spinor
represented this picture of a of a flag
so you have the flagpole goes along the
light cone so that's it that's the
vector like piece of it yeah it's a
vector and now and then you have an
extra piece of date an extra piece which
is this flag plane hmm and you get a
pretty good geometrical understanding
the one little catch to it is that if
you rotate it through 100 300 360
degrees so you might think just the way
it started it's not the same as it was
before it's it's changed its sign and
then you rotate it again that won't make
any sense to anyone but if I mean one
way of looking at that is if you have a
Klein bottle yes for those of some
people will be listening to this an
audience I'm watching it in video a
complying bar all in a certain sense
that can be made precise has a square
root that would be a torus that is
double color so it seems like a very
weird thing to take a square root of a
strange topological mobius like object
but there you are yeah so it's really
the square root of the rotations that
has this double effect but we say it
linguistically in a way that makes it
almost impossible for anyone to
understand I think this was a mystery I
mean I understood that spinner was the
square root of a vector you see and I
couldn't make head or tail of that idea
and it was when I went to Dirac's course
it did become clear and he made he gave
this very impressive illustration which
I thought was due to Dirac I learned
later it was just a Hermann Val hmm did
you imagine a cone
circular côtes yes it's based like that
circular cross section and another equal
cone which rolls on it so one is fixed
and the other one rolls around on it now
you see when you were imagine initially
the cone is almost just a little spike I
mean he was a tiny circle at the end and
when you roll one on the other it's like
rolling one coin on the other coin so
you and you can see when you roll one
coin another coin it goes around twice
because Marie's degrees as you go around
okay now when you imagine gradually
increasing the angle the semi angle of
the cone and you do it again you keep
thinking of that motion until it becomes
almost flat and then what's the other
one's just a little wobble all right so
when it becomes flat this motion goes to
nothing so this illustrates how a
rotation through four pi right two
complete rotations gradually can be
deformed into no rotation at all however
with single rotation it doesn't
disappear well I think with a with a
pulley system in a wheel we don't have
any trouble imagining the wheel that
rotates twice as fast half as fast not
at all hooked up to one particular crank
wheel right yeah the problem comes when
that that's not the generic case the
generic case is usually encountered one
dimension higher three and up has a
familiar because something called the
fundamental group as in structure Z mod
Z to Z in dimension two so there is
something where in the place where you
can see this most easily it's slightly
misleading and then in higher dimensions
you have to learn how to tutor your
intuition which is this problem at all
of us who try to think about higher
dimensional objects encounters that we
have to use the visual cortex we're
handed and then we have to trick it into
imagining worlds beyond where we've seen
but you see direct has another thing
that's not there's a thing called the
direct scissors problem mm-hmm
so you imagine a chair with which as the
pieces of wood going out like this
yeah and you have a pair of scissors I
think this is director joke there's a
pair of scissors and through the the
when you put your fingers you have a
piece of string which goes through this
and then goes around the chair and then
comes back through the other one goes
back again right now the problem is you
take the scissors and you rotate them
through 360 360 degrees and the strings
will tangle that we kill and whatever
you do you can't untangle it you're
allowed to move the sisters around
parallel not rotate them and you can
move the string around it and you can't
undo it but you do twice three hundreds
400-700 20 degrees to complete rotations
and then you find you can untangle it so
this was the direct scissors problem and
I think the trick the joke was it's a
pair of scissors so if you get super
frustrated and he wrote a paper
explaining that I think max Newman yeah
wrote a paper Dirac did this is an
illustration how you can undo it when
it's minutes right it's 4pi for someone
trainees degrees but to prove that you
couldn't do it with this is I think you
okay max Newman if you've seen this
video called air on the Dirac string
which illustrates this in video form
haven't seen I would highly recommend it
because it shows this off as the
similarity to the belt tricked the
foreseen wineglass yeah and it well is
all the different versions I find I
could do that one actually yeah I had
Joe Rogan try it yeah I think he got
almost all the way around yeah no I've
done it with a glass like that and it
comes back very stylish to to complete
rotations in the rotation yes so this is
a very fundamental property of the world
that is somehow not discussed I think I
find it very interesting that people
want to talk to me about the multiverse
sometimes they want to talk to me about
quantum measurement problem but the idea
that we are somehow based on a square
root and I would disagree with you
slightly if you would permit it it's not
just a question of the square root of
this of the vectors it's the square root
of the the algebra generated by the
vectors
that really this the spinners are this
exterior or Clifford algebra oh yeah
this object has fascinated me my entire
life and it's very strange that all of
you know the stability of matter and
matters strange properties with electron
shells are all coming out of this weird
not that it appears everywhere in the
universe and it's not universally known
that it's even there yeah it's the
difference between the family owns and
the bosons so the particles which have a
spin which is half an odd number right
which which have this curious property
that you rotate them and they get back
to manage themselves and it's crucial
for for matter because the Pauli
exclusion principle depends on the the
family statistics which is to do with
the this exact this property so without
this nodded miss and the scissor trick
or whatever you want to call it we
wouldn't have a periodic table and
chemical elements you didn't have
anything we'd have anything yeah you
wouldn't have it you wouldn't have
fermions in otherwise we wouldn't have
things which have an exclusion principle
so and the bosons which are the opposite
they they like to be on if you have two
bosons
in you can have them in the same state
make rather like to be in the same state
so you get these things called
bose-einstein condensates where if you
get the very coal they all flop together
into the same state but for the fermions
it's completely the opposite they hate
to be in the same state well they can't
be and this is what sort of pushes them
apart so you got the Fermi principle so
you have this path it's a strange thing
called the spin statistics theorem yes
that says that if things have a nodded
nosov a particular kind then they either
are highly individualistic or highly
communist stick whatever you want to
call it my question would be there's
another aspect of that that I've been
very curious about which is when we have
to treat these objects quantum
mechanically and you've of course
thought a great deal and quantum theory
we have two totally different
prescriptions for how to make these
different objects quantum mechanical but
there's a one-to-one correspondence
between these two
utterly different treatments that matter
and force get quantum mechanically it's
the darndest thing when you get these
two kinds of particle or two kinds of
atoms two bosons and the family owns an
inch has to do with the make a complete
rotation do they come back to themselves
or do they come back to minus themselves
that's the top of logic yeah but then
there's this whole swing out I go under
like bear is in integration which is no
integration at all I mean you're
effectively almost lying about what
you're doing to the fermions yes and
make them look like bosons and yet what
we what we seem to get out of this is
that nobody I I don't think anyone could
have anticipated that there would be a
dictionary of two totally different
structures which are seems to be almost
word-for-word yeah cuz they're not
totally different in the sense that you
take to a two-family out system and you
get the bosons so you well they have the
same well yes that's right no yeah maybe
I could ask you a little bit about that
mm-hmm so I want to get to supersymmetry
but before I do I said yes okay go on
we're gonna make you work this morning
so I can understand that yeah so here's
my question am I correct that you've
lived through two eras an era of fairly
rapid development in testable
fundamental physics coming from theory
I've tried to be very careful about
setting that up so I don't walk into a
trap and I a stagnant fear era in which
theoretical predictions coming at the
level of fundamental theory have not
been rapidly confirmed by experiment
you're thinking of things like string
theory I'm thinking about a regime
before the early 70s and a regime
following the early supersymmetry is
that what you meant well it could be
grand unified theory supersymmetry
Technicolor it could be asymptotic
it could be any one of a number of
speculative theories from loop quantum
gravity
regi calculus extremely reassuring think
we've tried a million different things
that don't they didn't really pan out
well it seems like well if you'll permit
an American metaphor
we've been waved into third base and
we've been waiting for the signal to
come home for about 50 years and we're
not even sure that anyone's still you
know there at home plate well you see
you might be wrong playing the wrong
game that's the trouble you think
rounders would do it well I mean there's
a lot of intriguing ideas you mentioned
basically I think you were hinting it
supersymmetry is one of them which but
maybe I've thrown off close to ten I
pretty pop I could do it pretty easily
but I guess you had there's nothing new
about that they were people were playing
around with not something I'm Kelvin
with the idea that nots might be at the
basis of particle identity yeah yeah I
mean these ideas come back again in a
different form but certainly in the I
guess the 19th century people were
playing with well I guess you can go
back further than that phlogiston well
that's true but I would say that Maxwell
was the first great condensation of
theoretical ideas where an enormous
amount of theory surrounding yeah
magnetism electricity visible light
invisible light well that was a huge
huge revolution that all of those things
now can be unpacked from a single
geometric equation but that's the thing
I mean people know about Galileo they
know about Newton you know about Kepler
they know about Einstein and they also
may know about the modern quantum field
theory Heisenberg Schrodinger people how
many people know about Maxwell not
enough not enough all the Maples do have
Maxwell's equations tattooed on their
backsides well some people do yes
but the general public don't know about
Maxwell but Maxwell's equations
completely changed our way of looking at
the world and we live off it without
thinking you know you've got these
lights here well these are visible
lights so we we know you knew my visible
right but we didn't know anything about
X rays x rays radio waves they're all
part of the same scheme electromagnetism
dynamic well some of this goes back to
Faraday just before makes sure
so Faraday had a lot of the influential
ideas electromagnetism well they're a
little bit of that was known before
Oersted knew that if you had an electric
current then you get a magnetic field
but it was the other way around with
Maxwell now if you have a varying
magnetic field you've got a current and
you combine these ideas you can make a
dynamo so these these things go to
Faraday and he has sort of clues that
there might be some connection with
light but he didn't have the equations
but even max you know I'm very partial
to this book on orchids that followed
Darwin's Origin of Species oh yeah that
was the book he wrote you the title is
and I always I love reciting it it's on
the various contrivances by which
British and foreign orchids are
fertilized by insects and so you think
well why would he write a damn fool book
like that after Origin of Species and
the answer is he wanted to test whether
he understood his own theory and in fact
it's revealed that he didn't understand
the full application I would say the
same thing is true of Maxwell's
equations which is this is perhaps the
best dress rehearsal for unification
we've ever seen you know full
unification and on the other hand it's
not until the late 50s that we actually
unpack the last trivial consequence of
the theory with the this bizarre effect
of passing an electron beam around an
insulated wire enough yeah in fact we
had dinner last night we we asked yucker
Aronoff hood if he wanted to come but
he's in Israel and he sends his regards
oh yeah
sent mine back oh I don't know he's
great fun I always but that was a that
was a very weird thing where we learned
that if you have a an insulated solenoid
that the phase of the electron beam
going in a circle around it would be
shifted despite the fact that the
electromagnetic field could be treated
as 0 because the electromagnetic
potential this precursor yeah
turned out to carry the actual content
that it before that it had been thought
that that was just a sort of a
convenience product to recover
electromagnetism and it turned out that
that geometric object was more important
and you know in part the reason I bring
this up is that we would have no way of
visualizing this effect if it were not
for your interaction with MC Escher and
there you have to explain that one well
you know this this this etching called
ascending and descending oh yeah sure
yeah which is sometimes referred to as
the Penrose stairs yes
well you want that story well thank you
but what I was gonna say about wire mass
yeah yeah yeah is that the photon is
really best represented in some sense as
the angles of a set of stairs like that
with this very mysterious property that
what you're really talking about is what
we would call horizontal subspaces
pictured as stairs and the fact that
there's a paradox of going around and
you seem to be going up all the time but
you're back to where you came is the
same thing as saying I never go up and
yet I come back higher or lower and
that's called Halle Nomi and we don't
have a means of visualizing that except
for like either rock-paper-scissors or
your work with Escher is that a fair
comment well I had is it the first time
you've ever heard somebody say this well
I mean there's a quite complicated story
hit her you see when I was a graduate
student in Cambridge I think it was in
my second year when the International
Congress of mathematicians took place in
Amsterdam
and so I and a few friends decided we
would go to this meeting and I remember
I think I was just about to get on the
bus or a tram or something and Sean
Wylie who is a lecturer in in algebraic
topology was just about to get off the
bus I was getting on he had this catalog
in his hand of an exhibition in the van
Gogh Museum
and this was a picture the one called
night and day with birds flying our
heart into the day in the night and they
checked it
the birds changed into the spaces
between the birds when we go and ice
look at this imagine that's amazing what
is that well they come from you know
well as you'd be very interested this is
this in the van Gogh Museum there is
this exhibition by an artist called Asha
so I've never heard of him before and I
went to this exhibition and I was
absolutely blown away I thought it was
most amazing thing I remember
particularly one called relativity where
people walk up the stairs of gravity
directions in two different ways
and I thought this was hugely impressive
and I went away thinking well I'd like
to do something impossible you see and I
didn't see I had an idea about an
impossible structure with bridges and
roads and things like that
so locally makes sense but as a whole it
was inconsistent and I didn't think I'd
seen anything quite like that in his
exhibition so I played around with this
and then I sort of whittled it down to
the triangle which people refer to as a
tribe are so it it's triangle which is
locally a completely consistent picture
but as a whole it's impossible and I
showed this to my father and then he
started drawing impossible buildings and
and then he came up with this staircase
so we decided we'd like to write a paper
together on this and we had no idea what
the subject was I mean what Peter said
the paper like this - what journal so he
decided since he knew the editor of the
British Journal of psycho
and he thought he'd be able to get it
through we decided the subject with
psychology of course is as you say it's
not if it's more in a way mathematics
because it's illustrates ideas well of
ecology and other things like that which
which I didn't quite know I was
illustrating at the time but anyway we
wrote this paper and we gave some
reference to a sure I think reference to
the catalog and my father sent a copy to
a friend a Dutch friend IRS's and he
managed to get it to Asia and then my
father in Asia had a correspondence so
that was this is Lionel Penrose Lana my
father Lana Penrose yes but I actually
visited Esha Tennant and he had sent to
print to my father with the dedication
to it and he gave me another so I and I
have in the body but in some sense
ceremony Museum you see I'm very
indebted to you for this for this reason
because when I when I have to describe
what general relativity is yeah and I
don't wish to lie the way everyone else
lies I'm gonna lie I'm gonna do it
differently I say that you have to begin
with four degrees of freedom and then
you have to put rulers and protractors
into that system so that you can measure
length and angle that gives rise
miraculously to a derivative operator
that measures rise over run that rise is
measured from a reference level those
reference levels don't knit together and
they form Penrose stairs and the degree
of Escher Nisour Penrose nests is what
is measured by the curvature tensor
which breaks into three pieces you throw
one of them away called the viol
curvature and you readjust the
proportions of the other two and you set
that equal to the amount of stuff now
that's a very long causal chain yeah but
it is linguistically an accurate
description of what general relativity
actually is yeah well let's trace that
it's also illustrates comb ology which I
was being interviewed
oh yeah years ago but I don't know
whether it's BBC I can't remember
was there was an interview was for some
reason they were interested in twister
theory now they think they're interested
well they thought me well I guess they'd
heard that word I saw Brian and at one
point they say well he surprisingly not
in the beginning they asked me what what
good it was you see what can you use it
for so I said oh you can use it to solve
Maxwell's equations you see then that's
equations of little Christian magnetism
and light and so they got a bit
interested they said oh how do you do
that well it actually involves an idea
that I couldn't really explain here it
it's not possible to you know in a sort
of popular talk about this no no what is
it exactly no no no I couldn't do it no
what's that
it's an idea it's something called Combe
ology no I could explain that so then I
went back at home and and I I was lying
my brain I thought I think I can't you
know it's this impossible triangle
that's exactly an illustration of karim
ology so i went back the next day and
told them that they weren't interested
they didn't use it i think i may have
tried to explain yes where you have a
look at something which is locally
consistent right but with an ambiguity
about it so here the ambiguities you're
not quite sure you draw a picture of it
the ambiguity is that you don't know how
far away it is it could be bigger and
further away or smaller and closer and
the picture is consistent but you get an
inconsistency if you go around right and
locally because you have a freedom yes
you misuse this freedom in a sense so
the glitch in it
is this impossible structure well I I
had this so this is actually my son and
my 14 year old son's copy of that book
yes and I was having to describe this to
him :
what calm ology was and I said that one
forms which is a piece of technology in
mathematics that you can analogize to
radar guns so that while you're driving
and the policeman shoots your car with
the radar gun he's measuring the
component of speed in the direction of
his gun yeah and so that's something
that eats the vector of speed and spits
out a number and you could imagine it a
racetrack that wanted to have a circular
series of radar guns to measure the
speed of cars going around now the
question is you also recognize that you
could build a poor man's version of a
speed system by heating the track to
some temperature and measuring how
quickly the temperature changes the car
went over but you can't actually have
the one thing that you want which is the
series of radar guns that are always
measuring the speed going around the
track because at some point if the
temperature is going down down down down
down down down then it's going to be ten
degrees below where ever it started
which is your paradox again yes well
there's something nice example somebody
made an ignorant remember who were you a
company you have a ball going up the
stairs or down it which everybody and
you accompany that with it with a a note
going up or down and you can make it
sound as though it keeps on going all
the way up and all the way up all the
time by the harmonics you're bringing
you how monican is you going right below
with it yes yeah sub perceptual so
there's this auditory illusion that
captures these yes you've have an
auditory version at the same thing and
something had this ball bouncing wrong
with that that's not me but that's a bit
of a cheat you I mean my point would be
that you're Escher stairs or you're
Penrose stairs are the the cheat is that
it appears to be flat in other words
it's very easy to achieve that on a
curved object but that what you did was
to create the illusion as taking place
in a plane or where you can draw it in
it in a rectilinear system if you have
an interpretation of a three-dimensional
thing which put you in an ambiguous and
so you saw the movie Inception of course
where they they realized this actually
yes they have an obsession but that
effect is the soul of the Aronoff Bohm
effect which surprised the world in the
late 50s because it was never so late
into the game it is it is a common same
sort of thing that's right well of
course like so many things people point
out that this Oscar righteous father
whose it was a Swedish artist had drawn
things like this before ah I think round
about the year I was born he had a
picture which is well with cubes going
around it wasn't exactly the same but it
was I've said I think I've seen these
photos the one with the cube tears and
then he had versions with stairs
staircases to never put an issue he
never put any perspective in it which
seemed to me that was a something missed
opportunity yes
no in my triangle I did put some
perspective yeah so this slightly you
can see but you can do it with a
perspective and it still works so what I
want to get at is I think also that we
have this very funny thing that happened
recently starting from the early 70s
where we started miss telling our own
physics history because of the needs of
the community to look like we were
succeeding when we weren't or we were
succeeding at something different than
we were trying to succeed at and in part
one of the reasons that I want to use
this podcast to discuss science is to
give alternate versions of what's
happened and I want to explore one or
two of them with you now you and I have
a very funny relationship which we don't
really know each other but you were
quite close to Michael attea at various
ways and I was we have graduate students
together and say in the same grew the
same year absolutely the same year it's
by the same supervisor incredible yes
that's right and then you continue to
cross-pollinate ideas yes
over the years yes for for listeners who
don't know Michael attea was one of the
absolutely most dominant and generative
I don't even know what to call him like
beyond genius a seer of type but he I
said she had such a broad understanding
of mathematics it's about me and
geometry more generally and analysis
they were just incredible and algebra he
wrote a book on on communitive algebra
the now he had a partner
for much of his career Isidore singer
who I was quite close to for a minute oh
yeah and is was again another one of
these figures that if I'd never met one
I wouldn't know that the human mind was
capable of that level of
repeated insight and they came up with
something called the Atia singer index
theorem which governs worlds in which
there are no time dimensions but only
space dimensions or no space dimensions
and only time dimensions but there's no
just equations without any differential
equations the differential equation if
you think about differential equations
is coming very often in three main
fields of study elliptic hyperbolic and
parabolic then the idea is that wave
equations would be hyperbolic the type
that you're worried about in physics but
things like soap films look like
elliptic equations and a TN singer had
this incredible insight into the nature
of elliptic equations do you that so now
I've got an extremely general theorem
which covers goes over all sorts of
different areas of mathematics and and
it has applications well it sort of
tells you that the the knotted nough
some beautiful space that you might be
exploring like some kind of high
dimensional donut that's knotted many
times around itself whatever you want
that that topological knotted miss tells
you something about the kinds of waves
that can dance on that space yeah no I
said it's a very remarkable theorem so
it means does that theorem in the so
called elliptic category world of space
in no time let's say relate strongly in
your estimation to the most important
hyperbolic equations that govern the
waves that make up our physical world
due to the constraints of relativity in
a world with one time and three spatial
dimensions well I can say if I used it
there and at least two different
continent contacts yes maybe more so I
mean I'm not an expert in that area at
all and it was mainly when I was trying
to solve a particular problem I don't
know how much detail you want to go into
these things it had to do with how to
make twister theory work in curved
spaces
but I ran up into a question which had
to do it has to do with complex geometry
so you've got geometry in which instead
of using real numbers to use you think
of measuring with rulers say and the
ruler is one dimensional the numbers go
along one dimension if you like and
complex numbers where you have the
square root of minus one incorporated
into the number system they're really a
two dimensional so the geometry of
complex numbers has twice as many as the
real numbers but the geometry of complex
numbers is particularly fascinating or
nicely Al Jarreau you might see the
analysis or whatever it is it's
particularly fascinating and I was sort
of when I learned about this when I was
at an undergraduate doing mathematics
and I thought it was an incredibly
beautiful because when you talk about
real numbers you have you can have a
draw curve which is a function so this
this curve has some shape and you might
want to see what is it a smooth curve
that means you have a tangent direction
as you go around it maybe it jumps so
it's not not even continuous but may be
smooth or it may be you have to have a
curvature of this curve and you might
might not be smooth enough to have
curvature C so if there's one degree of
smoothness or two degrees or you or you
can have three degrees or four degrees
and they're all different or an infinite
number of degrees or that you can expand
your function in the power series
they're all different and then we learn
about complex you see all we now do it
all over again and you've got your
analysis on algebra if you like geometry
where thee it uses complex numbers and
then suddenly you find that if it's
smooth everything comes with it you can
differentiate as many times as you like
you can expand as a power series and I
thought ask incredibly magic you just
have to do it once rather than is all
Craig all these different kinds I should
say the math
petitions yes quite often view the
complex case the name the case of
complex numbers as the natural case yeah
and the case of real numbers as
artificially tortured yes which is a
complete reversal from how most
engineers yes and you have actually have
been quite instrumental in making the
case for the fundamentally complex
nature that it's not just an envy me
instead physics but that nature appears
to be essentially complex I think you
see by just hearing this nature of
complex analysis right and how beautiful
it struck me as being and I've had this
sort of feeling wouldn't they be
wonderful if these numbers were somehow
the basis of way physical world operates
I have no reason to think that and then
I learned about quantum mechanics and I
was amazed to find yeah there they are
they're not just useful convenience you
can use them to simplify ideas and
mathematics you can you know might have
an integral you would have to work
awfully hard to get rid of yes but there
are things you find it you're a little
trick to do it now at least for me come
with contour integrals and they drop us
in an amazing way and I thought well
that's a piece of magic but it doesn't
tell you anything about the world it
just tells you this is a neat way of
doing things and then I learn about
quantum mechanics and suddenly these
numbers they're right there at the basis
of the whole subject and I thought that
was an amazing thing
maybe these complex numbers are really
there at the root of everything I mean I
think you wanted to talk about twisters
and yeah yes yeah maybe I can intro that
and then try to fit that into this
history that I'm claiming we don't tell
now one of the ways of describing what
twister theory is and of course it's a
bit of a tall order for a podcast um is
that you are replacing einstein's
space-time with a larger structure than
in sent in some sense implies space-time
where you can take all the data that
roams around on space-time the waves the
force the matter what have you and you
can
as mathematicians might say pull it
upstairs to this larger twister space
where you might have a couple of extra
tricks up your sleeve because the extra
space that you've created to augment
space-time with has this kind of complex
number aspect baked into it yes well it
was something I just to go back for a
moment if sure to explain the 80s singer
and that's why we see slowly I could
come to that in a minute because it's
it's a very interesting story the way
these things sort of come together and
take many many years sometimes before
they come together but I was really
intrigued by these complex numbers and
there is well something let me tell you
we saw the origin of the twister idea I
was struck by the fact that you see
people know that that when things travel
with a great speed and in in according
to Einstein special relativity they get
sort of flattened in the direction of
motion now this is a way of talking
about it and you get this Lorentz
contraction as its called
now I was playing around with relativity
and thinking about it was this two
component spinners and thinking about
the geometry of it worked and I realized
if you think of the sky you see the sky
is is where you have vectors in four
dimensions think of a vector or
something which has it has a magnitude
in the direction to it as well and into
ordinary space you've got this idea of a
vector which is quite common people know
about but when you're in four dimensions
then you have space and time together
but do you have particular vectors which
are called null and these are the ones
along the light-cone so these this is an
ordinary vector might represent a
velocity so you have a particle moving
along with a certain speed and your
four-dimensional vector would point
along the velocity or the momentum of
that particle so
weirdly in the space-time metric of
Einstein yeah these are vectors that are
not zero
but if you used in Stein's special
rulers and protractors what would the
length of these vectors a0 they would so
it's a really it's a it's linguistically
tricky to talk about these things
because they're nonzero things that
would be measured to be of zero length
if that concept of length was in fact
yeah extended from your normal concept
of length
yes the idea that something of length
zero means it's two points the distance
between them is zero you think of them
right on top of each other or if the
distance is very very small they're
pretty close to each other but in the
kind of geometry will call it minkovski
Jarmusch because although it's
describing Einstein's special relativity
the gym geometry was not an stein people
often say oh I'm son introduces
four-dimensional space-time that's not
true it was makovski and Einstein I mean
I heard that this is real this is not
just a sort of a weird artifact of the
description of various processes that
were being gonna test yes but it's a
kind of geometry and Mackowski showed
that the the space of special relativity
is really four dimensional and it's this
kind of geometry in which you can have
distances which is zero although the
points are a sort of long way away from
each other and this represents a light
ray so you have one event say and the
light through that reaches another event
when I say event I mean not just a
special position but the time as well so
you mean a position in space-time
space-time so you need four coordinates
three space in one time coordinate so
that's what we call an event and so you
have a point or an event in space-time
and imagine a particle moving with the
speed of light to another such event now
the distance between those two in these
kind of geometry that minkovski
introduced is zero so and he
we played around with different kinds of
geometry and he realized that special
relativity is really best described by
this kind of what we call minkovski in
geometry so you can have zero distances
and yet the points are not on top of
each other
so your idea was to take all the points
that are bizarrely zero just that's away
and then make those the new points in a
new space it wasn't quite that I have to
come up to this slowly because it's on
took years but the initial idea isn't so
hard to understand really you see if you
look out at the sky what do you see when
you're seeing light rays or you're
seeing photons coming to your eye which
have traveled with the speed of light so
the world line in four dimensions of
that photon is tilted over at what
represents the speed of light now in
this Minkowski geometry that distance
has a clear meaning so let me let me
give that the supposedly the photon is
emitted at one point when event and
received at another event now to that
photon the time between one and the
other is zero and that time measure is
exactly the distance measure in
Minkowski geometry suppose the particle
was not traveling the speed of light
suppose it traveled with half a speed of
light or some other speed then its time
experience of time is exactly the
distance according to minkowski's
geometry so you say if it travels with
very very very great speed suppose you
travel to a planet which is 4 light
years away and you travel with but I
won't do the calculation right here me
with half the speed of light then you
would the experience that you would of
time you experience is less than the
time that somebody here on earth would
think that it took you to get there so
as you travel faster you your experience
of the passage of time or slows down in
a sense you don't think it's as long and
if you actually travel the speed of
light that experience would be zero
so this is the experience of the length
of time if you add weight you could have
a very very good clock you carry with
you and you see how what clock made of
pure light it all gets pretty pretty
heavy out here well you don't make you
know you can measure the clock
it's a a nuclear clock or something and
you're not traveling with the speed of
light because you can't get this before
but the time measured by that nuclear
clock would be the distance in Minkoff I
should point out just for our listeners
yes even people who do this field of
differential geometry morning noon and
night in math departments almost never
choose to work in world with some
temporal and some spatial dimension yes
because it just it breaks your head it's
a very difficult different intuition
very different when you go back and you
think about the puzzles that people had
when Einstein right introduced his
special and most particularly general
relativity they found it very puzzling
you could see look at the arguments
people that well we keep using these
words like yeah I'm and length and all
of these things that have become we
don't recognize that in that one
innocent decision to break off one
degree of freedom and treat it
differently
that's right that all of our linguistic
intuition goes out yeah what's that all
over again
yeah well it was a curious experience I
had because I was giving a series of
lectures and see after all these were
the but our lectures given in what was
it they forget exactly what the dates
were maybe this roundabout nine nineteen
seventy or something like that and there
was a collection of mathematicians in
the collection physicists John Wheeler
and Cecile DeWitt had organized this it
was a very interesting meeting well
people from both areas of expertise were
brought together and at that time it's
hard to believe now but at that time
mathematicians and physicists were
barely talking to each other and they
got me to give us this series of
lectures and I decide you for Jim Simons
and CN yang get together and there's a
good question when was that I am billing
seventy five seventy say it was before
that
I'm listening before that's it right I
think so yes
I really have to have my memories dates
it's not like if you'll I know you're
you're hot on the on the trail of this
but just 211 something in Roman Jack Eve
at MIT once beautifully said um
and he'd I don't think I wrote it down
he said we used we didn't understand the
partnership that was possible between
mathematics and physics because we the
physicists used to talk to the analysts
and he said the analyst either told us
things that were absolutely trivial and
irrelevant or things that we already yes
he said when we talked to the geometers
we started to learn new things that we'd
never considered yes well it was very
much cross-fertilization there but I was
going to say I gave his lectures that I
think it was twelve lectures and I
wasted my time on something some weren't
going to and said I'd left myself only
three lectures to describe the
singularities the black hole idea which
wasn't the term black hole wasn't
useless then but the collapse you just
called the Schwarzschild singulars well
it was called the singularity when it
that was the thing people called it the
swatch of singularity which what we now
call a horizon right and I remember on
my third lecture from the end describing
the basically what we call a black hole
let's talk about the Schwarz singularity
and I was explaining that the Z it was
basically to do with a zero link
business and and steen rod was a very
distinguished mathematician he was
Princeton Norman steerer no yeah and he
had written this book on five abundance
which is absolutely impenetrable
impenetrable but also fundamental to the
subject yes but it's so impenetrable
that I never got to the point but anyway
he was there at the back of the room and
I remember telling Moses and he was
absolutely dumbfounded they see you
somebody who's a real expert at this
kind of german romanian geometry when he
would call it where you have the notion
of when the distance is a small then the
points are close together and here you
have this other kind of geometry and the
intuition you need for that geometry was
completely foreign as
point you were just making well because
yeah we do have this weird way of
talking about something that sounds like
this we might call it like non hausdorff
topology but it is a hausdorff topology
yes but it is it's it's so the problem
is is it's pulling apart two different
notions of the word close that's right
exactly that's right because you think
of close means a small distance right so
you imagine a little tiny ball where the
distance from that point is it was more
you know mathematics makes you pay for
every attempt to sort of intuitively
encode something that isn't precise
we've been discussing the fact that this
intuition is very very strange involving
how to think about spaces of the type
that Einstein and minkovski and Pangkor
a were considering yes how does that
begin to lead us towards these more
speculative ideas of yours surrounding
complex numbers and the twister program
I don't think many people many many of
them may have heard of it but even in
even in mathematic you have to know that
you got you were sort of seen as leaving
a cult it had its own newsletter its own
bizarre drawings it was very difficult
to communicate to members of the twister
cult because they didn't speak like
other people well we had this twisted
newsletter which was a it started off by
it's just in handwriting and it was
duplicated and then that's not going to
that for the moment are very good talk
about the basic the origin of twisters
here if you like how where did it come
from it was really in fact your big bet
in physics do you think yeah I think so
well you see it's between that and the
cosmology but the cosmology a bit
different because it not such okay it's
a wild idea yeah but it's not a whole
body of wild ideas which twist a theorem
or is all right
but it has lots of connections with
mathematics as pure mathematics and
connections with physics let me describe
the basis of it because I think we've
got most of the things we need you see
the light-cone describes how from one
point or one event in space-time all the
different
points of zero distance from it or
another with all the light rays from
that point now let me think about it the
other way around that is my past light
cone so I'm sitting at a certain point
in space-time and I look out at the
universe and all the light rays that get
to me as a particular instant moment of
my time come along this path like her so
that's imagine this kind of stretching
out into the past and getting bigger and
bigger as it goes back in time and
that's all the events which are in one
moment of my time I was I see those
events so I see a lot of stars in the
sky now let's suppose that I mean this
stars and sky look like points you see
so that you have the sphere the
celestial sphere which is my field of
vision if I'm imagining myself out in so
imagine that the earth was transparent
so you weren't that's one way oh let's
go out into space then I guess I can be
looking at the world all around me now
let's imagine that another astronaut
comes whizzing past me at nearly the
speed of light and just as we passed
each other he looks he or she looks out
at the sky at the same moment as I do
now because of a phenomenon known as
aberration the Stars will be slightly
not in the same place with regard to
that astronaut as me this guy is
somewhat distorted but it's distorted in
a very particular way which is what's
called conformal a way say this in a
simple way suppose I happen to see a
configuration of stars that happened to
me on a circle suppose they work
encyclopédie these in a circle even
though the transformation would not be a
rotation of the sphere sky would be
squashed up more on one end and
stretched out on the other end but the
thing about that transformation it's
something which I knew about from my
complex analysis days do you think of
the what's called the Riemann sphere
this is the plane of points it's a
complex plane or the vessel plane are
the point at play the points represent
the complex numbers so zero is in the
middle if you like and then you've got
one
and then you've got minus one and I and
minus I are all on the circle and you go
out and infinity is way out to infinity
but the Riemann sphere folds all this up
into a sphere so infinity is now point
just a little bit like if you have a if
you have a caramel coating around an
apple you're folding that you've wasn't
around us and at the point where the
stick would go into the Apple all of the
boundary of that candy would come
together yes and it's what's called a
stereographic projection you can project
from the North Pole and all the other
points flatten out into the plane so you
can see all the points on the sphere
except for the point from which your
project exactly and that's called the
stereographic projection and it has this
remarkable property that it sends
circles to circles or you could say it's
conformal that is angles are preserved
and it's a very beautiful transform a
used to play around with these things
just for fun of them now the thing is
that the transformations of this sphere
to itself which preserve the angles is
also transformation which is what's
called analytic or column holomorphic
it's it's the most smooth transformation
you can have so just the analog of
smooth but free complex objects rather
than real objects and where real and
complex means the types of numbers yes
that's right so it's search what's what
smooth is and complex analysis and those
transformations which send the sphere
the sphere are exactly those in
relativity
so the different observers passing me at
different speeds looking at the same sky
the map from my sky to their skies is
exactly these complex transformations of
the sphere and this actually is what you
exactly get when you use two component
spinners and you see the description
when you move from one observer to
another is exactly those ones which
transform the sky in this conformal way
to itself and often people find this
puzzling I find it puzzling recently
because suppose you had a sphere which
is whizzing you know an alien spaceship
which is a sphere shooting past you at
nearly the speed of light well you see
the direction of motion it will be
contracted by the Lorentz contraction so
when you look at it you should see it
sort of flattened out you don't because
a sphere goes a circle goes to a circle
if you see it as a circle when it's not
moving you'll still see it as a circle
and the boundary of a thing will look
like a circle which is moving and you
work away and think about it well you
see where the light waves go and the
front of it in the back of it and you
see really you don't see the flattening
it really it doesn't look like it like I
said a circle its boundary looks like a
circle so I wrote a paper on this almost
simultaneously there wasn't somebody
else wrote a paper mainly thinking of
the small circles and spheres but this
transformation that was really what
started me off if I understand correctly
maybe I don't yeah we have another
mutual acquaintance a friend Raul Bhat
and yes he showed us that the world
seems to repeat every eight dimensions
in a certain way but during the first
cycle of what you might call baat
periodicity from zero to seven or one to
eight depending upon how you like the
cat yeah yeah you get these things
called low dimensional coincidences oh
yes and so that that they don't recur
because of your point earlier about
spinners that spinners grow yes
exponentially whereas vectors grow
linearly that's right and but during the
first period where these things are of
comparable strength yes you've get all
of these objects where depending upon
you define in two different contexts you
turn out to be the same object that's
not are you're making use of that here
it is that it's the well the Lawrence
group we're like you know that the
rotations of space and time
which we might call so1 three or so1
three double cover would be equal to
something else called SL to see which
would mention complex numbers even
though there's no complex numbers to be
seen in space and time yeah it depends
on that that one of those coincidences
what's triple coincidence I think you
said answer which one is depending upon
in this description but the point I'm
making here is that in a certain sense
relativity is described when you do it
in the two spinner form which is really
expressed in this fact that it's the
transformation of the Riemann sphere to
itself which is a complex transformation
this is the most general transformation
of the sphere to itself when you think
of that sphere as a Riemann sphere so
it's a complex one-dimensional space you
might say surely it's two-dimensional
well it's two-dimensional in real
numbers but one-dimensional and complex
numbers because the complex each complex
number us carries the information of two
real number so for example
mathematicians would call what most
people call the complex plane they might
call it a complex line it's complex line
that's right yeah and so the language
again is intended to make things very
hostile to the newbie
yes right that's true but you have to
get used to the idea that when you're
thinking complex when you think of it
sort of really sort of concretely in in
their real terms
that you have to double the number of
real dimensions to get the number of
complex but I want my audience laugh but
I don't want them to feel stupid for
making the mistake every one person you
have the number of good so we have the
complex numbers playing a fundamental
role in relativity that's the really
point I wanna make and it's the complex
sphere so the Riemann sphere which is
this one-dimensional in in complex sense
two-dimensional in the real sense object
which is fundamental now this Riemann
sphere appears in the most basic way in
quantum mechanics to you think of the
spin now that's the practically in the
most direct conflict the most direct
quantum-mechanical thing in a certain
sense where you see quantum mechanics
playing a real role as quantum mechanics
which is hard to grasp normally but you
can see it here is the geometry really
works you see if you have an object of
spin 1/2 that's the smallest nonzero
spin you can have such an electron so
think of an electron it has been half
now what that means is that it's
basically two states of spin which
people call spin up and spin down well
what does that mean right hey put your
thumb up like they're right-handed spin
is where your fingers go
and that's spin up means right hand is
about up spin down is right hand is
about down oh that's left-handed about
that and those are the two basic states
but what's special about up and down
nothing so you think of what about right
left forwards backwards all those are
combinations of up and down and there
are complex combinations through these
complex numbers which lie at the basis
of quantum mechanics but here you can
see in a visual way what they're doing
you see you can say up down what's left
and right where these are combinations
have up and down so you add this much of
up to that much of down and you get to
the to the right right and and you - it
you get to the left or I times you get
forwards about whatever it is and the
complex numbers come in to describe
these possible directions of spin and
it's the Riemann sphere again so you but
you were relating these complex numbers
of quantum mechanics do the directions
in space so you have a connection
between these rather abstract numbers
which are fundamental to quantum
mechanics and the much more concrete
picture of the directions in space Wells
but Roger I think you're both well let
me be challenge you slightly go on yes
what you're really talking about is a
very important fork in the road for
physics do you wet yourself to the world
that we're actually given and you know
Mach was famous
for having said this phrase the world is
given only once and so we happen to know
that there does exist a world that
appears to be well modeled by three
spatial in one temporal dimension that
and then the key question is do you wish
to have a more general theory which it
works in all dimensions or which works
for all different divisions between how
many spatial on how many temporal
dimensions and what I see you is having
done which I think is incredibly noble
brave and scientifically valid is to
work with mathematics that are really
particular izing themselves to the world
we're given rather than sort of keeping
some kind of I mean like you're getting
married
to the world we live in in a way that
other people are just dating it and
wishing to keep their options open I
think you've hit on a very crucial point
absolutely right I mean for example with
string theory know that people talk
about 26 dimensions or 10 spatial
Dermott or 11 or 12 and things like that
and sure the mathematics we've got
mathematics to handle these things and
maybe that's important the way the world
works
but I was never attracted by that that's
for basically two reasons one was the
reason I'm just trying to subscribe here
and it's exactly what you're saying that
I'm looking for a way in which you find
the mathematics to describe the world
which is very particular to the
dimensionality we see so the three space
dimensions and one time dimension is
described in this formalism very
directly and if you're going to try and
talk about other numbers of dimensions
of space and time it doesn't work well
as much as I really like to stick it to
the string theorist
yeah that's not exactly their problem
either because 26 is really because
that's two more than 24 and 10 is really
because it's two more than eight and an
eight you have something special called
try ality yes and so what they were
really doing was figuring out how to
build different theories around
different highly specific targets but
you see there it's the beaut
mathematics which sure well is a good
guide but it has to be leaving with any
reason they never grow up to playing
with reality that's the sort of thing I
mean it's it's perfectly good to explore
all these different things and it's very
valuable but I'm trying to follow a
route which is viewed I think in many
quarters is very narrow I'm looking for
a route which is work specifically for
the number of space-time dimensions that
we have and is if I'm there aspects of
Twister theory which do work in other
dimensions but they run out very quickly
and you can see analogs of these things
but they kind of the wrong version of
the entropic principle which is that if
there weren't a beautiful mathematics
just to catch you I mean in some sense
despite the fact that you're in your
late 80s it's like you're stage-diving
in a punk concert where you're kind of
hope that the mathematics catches you
because you're willing to actually marry
in a very deep level the world that we
do observe and I find that what what's
very disturbing to me is that the
political economy of science means that
fewer people are willing to make strong
speculations strong predictions to
explore things that don't give them the
flexibility in case things that don't
work out to say well it could be like
this it could be like that and so in
part I see you as part of a dying breed
of people who are willing to go down
with a ship for the privilege of
commanding it as its captain well you
can do it that way if you like my claim
is that the sick ship isn't actually
sinking you might think you know no no
I'm not I'm not really I think that one
of the things that that's happened is
has been that yours has been one of the
most important idiosyncratic programs
that in fact got a huge lease on life
from the fact that it has positive
externalities because it was absolutely
solid mathematics it turned out that
even if it doesn't give us a fundamental
description of the world it is at least
a deep
insight into how to transform one
problem into another to allow solutions
that wouldn't have been easily gleaned
in the FIR and original formulation yeah
I'm not saying that it's it's knocked
out of the park for a fundamental theory
but I I don't actually know whether do
you believe twisters are a more
fundamental description of the world
well I do yes I mean I know I don't
normally say that out loud but now
you've put me in a position yes no I
think that's yes fucking great I mean in
other words it's like you have to say
this I believe and in general people
won't say it yeah I think the thing is I
have been driven in directions as just
as you're pointing out in directions
which picking out the particular rather
than the general right so sure you have
mathematics which one of the huge aims
in mathematics be more and more general
and you mentioned the Atia singer
theorem that's a beautiful example of
that where it simply generalizes of over
areas which you would never thought but
it also particular eyes so for example
yes it is only in low dimensions where
you get to play the game with what are
called deformation complexes where the
first term is the symmetry is the
problem the second term is the fields or
the waves and the problem and the third
term is the equations and the problem
and then you get to cut it off at that
point and have that be with this magical
concept of an elliptic complex so for
example in dimension 4 we gleaned
something bizarre which is that there an
infinite number of different ways to do
calculus in four-dimensional space and
only one way to do it in every other
dimension yes yes well there's something
special they are about for certainly
that's true and the connections maybe
not that clear at the moment but maybe
we will see that this is it may be
differentiable structures are more of a
part of physics it's it's quite possible
how amazing that yeah I'll give you
another very bizarre one I don't know
whether this has ever come up if you
have two sets of symmetries known as Li
groups that act transitively
on the same sphere in usual position
then either their intersection acts
transitively on that sphere or the
dimension of that sphere is 15 and I
believe that the intersection of the
groups looks like the electro strong
group so it's very close to the particle
spectrum of theoretical physics yeah
pulled out of nowhere just from talking
about severe transitive grouping well
it's clear that one I mean in particle
physics I mean I've never really been
somebody who studied particle physics
closely is that right I didn't know well
I mean in general where I have but but I
suppose I felt we're maybe a long way
from really understanding what's going
on there I don't know I mean I hope I
hope that it wasn't that well you know
we have no it's a completely I often
have although different views from one
of these things I think we're almost at
the end well that's an interesting scene
so how do you come to the idea that we
may be quite far I'm not saying that
we're necessarily far I think it's
understanding why the groups are the
groups that we see and people have
different theories about these let me
ask you then a couple of questions it's
go on so very early in this new
stagnation post the standard model
people like Glashow and george i and
patty and salam put forward these
unifying symmetries that remain very odd
because they're so attractive and
powerful the the prettiest of them being
something called spin ten which
physicists persist in calling s o ten
for reasons that escape me yeah well
this is the one which doesn't exist or
is that not that one well the original
su five which sits inside of spin ten
was disproven in its most basic form and
at that point
george i and Glashow had been trained in
the previous culture of physics which is
that you fell on your sword when you
predicted something and it wasn't true i
think that they sort of rushed to commit
ritual suicide far too quickly yeah I
just
maybe if I worked in the subject
form of clear review it's just from the
outside I'm not convinced that
completely there there are things which
people have discovered was shown
absolutely fundamental in particle
physics but somehow it hasn't got to the
basic level which I feel I can see why
these groups of what they are and so on
let me not talk about it because I'm not
an expert at that they're not only
giving an impression and I suspect there
will be maybe not too long from now a
better understanding I'm hoping that was
a theory might have something to say
about it but at the moment the area
which needs to be explored here hasn't
been explored the things we did at one
time I'm sort of deviating a bit from
the general trend but there was a
question of how we trate trate how we
treat massive particles in twister
theory and naturally twister theory
describes massless things things go
along the light-cone and that sort of
things with others because you
privileged the like owns it yeah then
the treatment of particles that were
massless got a privileged treatment
privileged treatment and not just that
you find transformations there is a way
of representing the Maxwell equations
this is the thing that was mentioning
about the TV program way of describing
the Maxwell equations which you get out
of twister theory and it comes directly
out then what about the Dirac equation
you want to talk about massive particles
well then where it seems to lead you as
you think of the we see a massive
particle has a momentum that which is
time like so points within the cone and
one way you can describe a time like one
is think of to look no one soar to light
like one so you think of a zig zag
so it's got a zig and a zag and that's
one convenient way Jake or you might
have one which is made of three
zigzagged
dog something like that and you can get
at the time like line out of so you can
build it up from different primitive
that's right so the argument is that you
have a twister for each of these zigs
and zags
and so you have might have two of them
you might have three of them and you see
how many of them give you the same
amount and then you get these groups in
twisted theory and these groups look
like the particle physics groups so you
get su 2 and su 3 and the idea we has oh
well that's the basis for these parties
so su 2 doesn't impress me much because
it's ubiquitous but su 3 is a very nice
on you this is the the group that
represents the strong force then holds
our yeah well you see there's the thing
that su 3 gives you this gate you can
gauge it so you have there is a
difference between the su 2 and the su 3
that that the quantum chromodynamics if
you like which is the theory which comes
from gauging su 3 is a genuine gauge
theory but when you try and do it for su
to the left for the electrons and we can
weak weak isospin you either gauging it
doesn't really work because you've got a
better special it's not the full group
so on so there's something funny about
it okay and there are other theories
which might be a more promising way to
go let's not go into that because this
is all guessing but the idea is that you
could develop a particle physics using
many twisters gonna have it in in other
words if I'm not misunderstanding you
the idea is that the extra data I mean
we have a problem
in the standard model yeah in that we
have effectively a an origin story with
two gods there's the god of Einstein
that gives us space and time and then
there's this other god that gives us su
3 cross su 2 cross u 1 which give us the
non-gravitational forces and all of
these particle properties we call
quantum numbers and this has no
connection to the space and time data
well that's the sort of thing yeah yeah
it looks as though it's quite separate I
mean they must be tied up at some stage
but we haven't got to that but the idea
here was to try and do it via twisters
well I'm just trying to say that we had
we were got very excited about this for
a while and then it was a long time ago
because when people discovered
come I think it was charming to suddenly
this didn't fits and so we gave up at
level and so by charm you mean the the
addition of entirely separate versions
of the familiar family of matter so we
now think we have three copies of matter
yeah we're the second two are repeated
at higher mass get that sort of thing
yes yeah that's right
and so people go I mean it didn't seem
so simple at that point so and various
things didn't seem to fit so well but I
think we should go back to that from the
insights that going from general
relativity I mean there's a long story
which should be probably hard to
describe here but the construction see
Twista theory starts off as a theory
about space flat space-time that's what
bothers me about it exactly and that's
what bothers a lot of people when you
see very good company that I was at the
time at the University of Texas for a
year and this Alfred shield had put a
lot of people together who were relative
general relativity experts hoping that
something would come out of it I guess
and I had an office next to angle about
cooking we might learn a lot from
[Music]
and on the other side I had an office it
was Roy curse office and Ray Sachs was
all the way down and I have to backtrack
because the question is where did where
did Twista theory come from now I had a
lots and lots of ideas that I was trying
to fit together part of these were
trying to combine the Riemann sphere of
relativity with the Rema sphere of
quantum mechanics and various other
mathematical ideas which come into
quantum field theory and I they were
sort of floating around and I remember
drawing a big piece of paper with all
these ideas which were roughly speaking
of the nature that the world we see is
described by real numbers but sort of
hiding behind it is a world of complex
numbers and they somehow
control this world of real numbers so
the dynamics is somehow controlled by
the way the complex numbers work this
was a vague thought I had and I couldn't
think of a picture in which you added
you see space-time has four dimensions
and I needed to add basically one more
dimension because I wanted to
incorporate the idea again it's
difficult to describe these things on a
sort of popular program but it was an
idea fundamental to quantum field theory
which has to do with splitting your
field amplitudes into positive and
negative frequencies and it's a anger
birth had been pressed upon me that this
was very fundamental to quantum field
theory most people weren't stressing it
at that time and the way to think about
this is think of the Riemann sphere
again and you have the equator of the
Riemann sphere describing the real
numbers together with an infinity and
you've got this complex numbers on one
side and one Hemisphere and what's on
the other hamster and the ones which are
positive frequency which is the
fundamental thing for quantum field
theory extend into 1/2 so this to me was
a very beautiful way of thinking about
it rather than splitting everything into
Fourier components and taking taking
half of them and that was seen to me you
have four degrees of freedom with one
extra real degree of freedom one extra
dimension like the Riemann sphere going
from the you have to the whole sphere
yeah and I wanted it to divide it in two
halves yeah and that was the picture I
wanted and you tried to do the
space-time it doesn't work was first my
space-time is four-dimensional and if
you complexified say dimensional that
doesn't divide into this just something
else so I I knew that wasn't right okay
now I was in Austin Texas I had friends
in Dallas now this was the year in which
Kennedy was assassinated and my friends
in Dallas were to dinner and it was the
next place that Kennedy was to go to and
he was going to give a speech and they
all got worried because he didn't turn
up and they were generally quite right
to be worried because he'd been shot
and this was a great shock to us all and
so we decided we wanted to count myself
down and wins a trip to trip from Austin
where I was and Dallas where the others
were and we went off in a few cars to
San Antonio and maybe to the coast and
this was to try and recover from the
shock and coming back that all the women
folk wanted to gossip and so on and I
was with pish-tosh part he was a nice
fellow I liked him a lot
and garyun but he didn't speak much so
well there are others when to gossip and
I was sort of left over and we with the
two of us went in the car driving back
to Austin and so I had a nice silent
drive coming back and I started to think
about these constructions that I've
already and he was in Dallas at the time
an English fellow who lived in Dallas
and he constructed these solutions of
the Maxwell equations which had this
curious twist in them and I understood
these things and I realized that they
were described by as you talked about
the hops map are they Clifford parallels
these are you can think of a sphere in
four dimensions three dimensions clear
four dimensions and you have these
circles which fill the whole space no
two intersect and they every to link
beautiful configuration and I realized
that this was the thing that
geometrically described these solutions
that IRA had found and I tried to think
about this and I thought well okay these
sort of describe well the way I've all
had to fit all of us to think of it
think of a light ray yeah and then you
think of all the light rays which meet
that light ray so you've got a one light
ray and all the other slight trace was
metered and that family of light ray is
you can have Maxwell's solutions and max
which point along those rays so what he
did this was his trick you move that
light ray into the complex so you add a
complex number to thee to two extra
dimensions well it pushes the light ray
into the complex
then you can construct this twisting you
don't see the light ray anymore
expression to the complex but you've
still got the complex family of light
rays which meet it in a certain sense so
I try to understand what that looks like
and I thought this is yeah you're
pushing something into the complex and
you describe it by means of this
complicated twisting family of right
marries so I in the drive back I thought
well let's count the number of
dimensions there are these as I call
them later Robinson congresses and I was
gratified or startles or whatever the
right word is to find that the number
the number of dimensions of these
conquer this my family right which was
six six dimensional family what's the
dimension of family of light rays five
so the ones you actually see directly in
the light rays that's the real thing and
the thing which governing in the
mysterious complex world add one
dimension they can twist right-handed
that's one way left-handed it's the
other way divide something into exactly
what I was looking for fantastic
I got in that and then additionally had
this structure of three complex
dimensions yes yes well I went I had to
go back and get hold of my blackboard
and trying to work it out no and I'm
exhilarated so it was it was a complex
projective three space you have these
two twisters and I know pretty chuffed
with myself didn't realize what this was
you have a five dimensional space which
divides this six real dimensional space
which is really a three complex
dimension space into two half so if I'm
understanding you you would start out
off with a seven dimensional sphere you
take an action by a circle to get see
the complex projective three space and
then you could further quotient that out
by two spheres to get the four
dimensional sphere well yes you have to
have oh you can think of it as a sphere
and maybe I'm not seeing it correct you
can't think of it as a sphere and
probably you at a complex projected yeah
yeah you can think of a seven sphere now
let me just tell you what I find
fascinating about this story is that
you're talking about a pea
traveling between two cities where you
realize something is the hopf fibration
well you it was a hot foundation but I
hadn't actually thought of it you may
not know the following no go ahead yes
yes Isidore singer took the work of Jim
Simons and Frank yang yeah yeah yeah and
on the trip to Oxford where you Michael
work yes he said oh my god this is the
quarter jnana crathers an the complex
hopf fibration he said it was about nice
instantly when he realized that the
self-dual instant-on equations were
going to be a revolution and so it was
the exact moment of the relationship to
something is non-trivial in his case as
the quaternion ik rather than the
complex hopf fibration so this is almost
an exact parallel between two stories
because I've never heard yours be that's
very interesting it also has relevant
direct relevance direct yes because I
think as we were just saying because you
think of the vector space for which the
complex three space and of course that's
for complex dimensions and then that
means eight real well so and this is
look I want to tie this into a bigger
thread which i think is fascinating I am
NOT a devotee of string theory nor am I
of loop quantum gravity I think that
most of what has been said about
supersymmetry has been overbearing and
wrong
I completely agree with all those things
you say and I think that the
intellectual carnage from these
adventures in political in political
economy or public relations or whatever
you want to call it are not being borne
by the people who benefited from them
but by those who have to clean up after
it's something to be said well you don't
have to say it I have to know that
because I'm not inside of the
universities yeah no yeah now what I
would claim yeah is is that while these
people I think did a tremendous
disservice for all of us taking what I
consider to be our most accomplished
intellectual community in the history of
academics theoretical physics it is not
the case that these people did nothing
for 45
years but what they did do has never
been told properly so I claimed to you
at dinner and the other night mmm like
if you just look at the role of
curvature in our understanding of not
only general relativity where it's been
for over a hundred years
mm-hm but now in particle theory so we
had a first revolution around the
mid-1970s with what's called the Wuyang
dictionary where a particular geometry
comes the most successful hedge fund
manager in human history
meets arguably the most accomplished
theoretical physics physicist if it's
not Weinberg it might being in terms of
what has been proven this contributions
they have an unbelievable interaction
which shows that the classical theory
underneath particle physics is as or
more geometric than the theory of
Einstein using steen rods fiber bundles
in Eris mons connections or vector
potentials or what have you then you
have a second revolution again involving
so that was the first one that is Singer
takes from Stony Brook to Augsburg
yes you have another one yeah which is
the geometric quantization revolution
with your colleague Nick Woodhouse
writing the Bible there yes yes in which
Heisenberg's uncertainty relations
strangely come out of curvature rather
than just being some sort of heaven you
look in connection in a bundle well that
there's this thing called the pre
quantum line bundle where line is
against one of these planes of the
terminologies all screwed up
yeah nevertheless the key point is is
that what we had previously treated as
the annoyance of the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle became the beauty
of a geometric quantum so now you had
the underlying classical theory is
geometric the underlying quantum theory
is now geometric and then again with
your English group particularly Graham
Siegel's is that is a real hero with
michael Latia pointing the pointing the
way
you guys figure out that this weird grab
bag that was called quantum field theory
which is this thing above quantum
mechanics that is needed for if you're
going to have particles that change
regimes in which the number of particles
changes like something emits a photon
unique quantum field theory you can't do
it in quantum mechanics so that world
was a grab-bag that made absolutely no
effing sense pedagogically to anybody
coming from outside of the discipline
and what they taught us and this is
coming from the the 1980s on is is the
quantum field theory would have been
discovered by topologists and geometers
even if the physical world had never
used it because it was actually a
naturally occurring augmentation of
what's called board ism theory which is
an enhancement of what you previously
referred to as comala ji so these are
three separate revolutions with people
that almost nobody's ever heard of like
Luis Alvarez Gamay and you know and Dan
Quillin who I think is the world's
greatest accidental quantum field theory
for some reason the physics community is
still telling us stories about
entanglement and about multiverses and
many-worlds and this actual thing that
happened which is as gorgeous as
anything I've ever seen has been a
revolution that's been plowing through
mathematics and physics is covered up
because they want to tell a story about
quantum gravity which just doesn't hang
together what the eff yeah I think I'm
worried about my wildly off no I don't
think you are you see I mean a lot of
these things that I wish I knew more
about you see for example Coulomb theory
and so on which which you know life is
too short but but these askings out of
the attea singer theory where yeah he
finds these determinant lines which are
coming out of non-local spectral
information and building the basis maybe
for pre quantum line bundles in which
the
actions in that world become the waves
that give us the theory I think the
trouble here you see mathematics is full
of all sorts of beautiful deep theory
and most of mathematics as it exists now
in the sense of what's written in
journals and so on has almost no bearing
on the physical world now you see I feel
totally convinced and I think you're
expressing something similar that if you
find the right route through this stuff
you will really find the key to what
we're seeing in the physical world now
we've found many such keys and general
relativity to the Lorentzian version of
romanian semi romanian or pseudo Romani
yes silly romanian geometry so that's
picked up a beautiful area of
mathematics and turned it into into
physics and it's and then but in
reverses has given a lot back to
mathematics and also with quantum
quantum theory clearly and quantum field
theory meant but me I think there are
things they are hiding there which are
very beautiful mathematics and which
will reveal themselves as important in
the physics where you haven't got to it
what do you make of the fact that we now
have three separate geometries so you
have Romani in geometry as the parent of
general relativity yes you have eros
money in geometry which is based on sort
of these Penrose stares coming from
fiber bundle theory which is the parent
of the Maxwell classical theory but also
the classical theory that would be
underneath the strong force holding
protons together one want to repel and
the weak force which causes beta decay
all right and then you've got this other
geometric theory which is the geometric
quantum and they're not the same
geometry so for example the geometry
that the Jim Simons and CN yang find has
this property called gauge symmetry you
have the opportunity for gauge
tree in the Einstein theory but because
Einstein takes curvature and uses
something called linear algebra to
project all of the curvature information
into a smaller subset killing off
something called viol curvature if you
gauge symmetries and then project it's
not the same as projecting and then
gauge symmetry so the opportunity to use
gauge theory is lost by the specific
genius of Einstein well you see there's
a good example because he did this
amazing thing when producing general
relativity but then in his later years
he tried to develop the theory and his
unified field theory switch from a
mathematical point of view was not
really a very it's not likely to give
much new insights but you know he was
right to think you should find a unified
scheme and so on and bring the well he
troubled one trouble as he didn't really
he considered electromagnetism but the
particle physics didn't play much of a
role in what he was doing well he died
before quarks weren't but that's
assuming he never he was innocent of su3
in its various yeah yes I think the
thing is there's huge beautiful things
in mathematics and we'd like to think
and I like to think that they do have a
role in fundamental role roles that
we've not yet discovered in operating
weather work well the way the world
works
is dependent on very deep mathematics
the trouble is that there's so many
wrong steps in the sense that many
beautiful things in mathematics which
are guided in certain directions which
from the point of view of mathematics
are great and they can be generalizing
ideas and and revealing all sorts of
previously unknown beauties but the
proportion of these which we find has
relevance to physics it's so it's very
small at the moment now I think that in
some ways maybe the most powerful the
most sure having complex numbers
and the analysis of complex numbers is
one example where he once does seem to
see a role in operating the way the
world works and I'm sure there we will
find other things it's just there are so
many temptations in directions which are
not particularly to do with this I
understand that but what I don't
understand and what I'm absolutely
unsympathetic with is that we have a lot
of people who once upon a time had a lot
of different ideas now most of the ideas
at the moment we're brutally honest it
we are so constrained by this point in
our story in theoretical physics that
almost every new idea is dead on arrival
unless you specifically keep it from
predicting things that we don't see yo
yeah right and so what I see is is that
you've got different and this is a
sociological and economic critique is
that you have a class of naughty boys
who are very badly behaved who get to
make all sorts of claims who talked to
the press incessantly over decades about
all the wonderful things they're going
to do which they don't do and then you
haven't got another group of people
whose feet are held to the fire where
the instant they start to consider
something that might for example violate
a no-go theorem they're roundly
humiliated now what I see you is having
done is to carve out a very unusual
niche twister theory is at a minimum an
incredibly valuable tool for generating
solutions on one space from solutions on
another let's say however it's also
somewhat tolerated within the system
it's a minority point of view it's a
minority community but it is allowed to
play a parallel game to the string world
where the string theorists have lived
for years in my estimation on
externalities there are lots of positive
externalities of having and I do think
that's the smartest community out there
I do think that in general they're
smarter than the relativists they're
even smarter than most of the geometers
they're in
sufferable they're very clever people
yeah very good okay so I'm very
insufferable oh yeah and the problem
with that community is is that it's
actually accomplished a great deal that
isn't of a stringy nature that's true
yes and I do think that what they've
done is they've instead of quantizing
geometry which is what quantum gravity
was supposed to be they it backfired and
they they had the geometry geometry is
the quantum and that's the main legacy
of these people is it something that
they you know they they took off for for
Paris and landed in Tokyo which is very
impressive as a feat but it wasn't what
they were setting out to do I I think
basically I agree with that and
certainly string theories had a big
influence in various areas of
mathematics but the influence directly
in physics has been pretty minimal
thinking what do you think about the
legacy of something like supersymmetry
which is that's an interesting question
isn't it yes what's very interesting
partly from a personal point of view
because when I first heard about it and
a lot of it was on conformal
supersymmetry right and I could see
there was a lot of connection with
Twista theory the only thing I didn't
like was you were led to these algebras
which didn't commute and well you there
was the square of something with zero or
something whatever I mean they weren't
the kind of algebra that you needed in
twisted theory you needed complex
analysis but anyway I went I visited
zoomy know at one point and I wasn't
most intrigued because I could this is
half of the duo that came up with a sort
of originally original deep well yes a
supersymmetric model absolutely yes and
so I thought there's enough connections
here I'd like to understand it better
and yeah I think I understood a bit more
but one thing I remember particularly
this is a little bit of a side point but
I was talking about two component
spinners and I realized he was somebody
who understand it understood it
perfectly well and he told me this story
he said he once written the paper in
which he
two component spinners and it was worked
out very well
a few months later Abdul Salam did the
same thing but using four component
spinners and he said everybody referred
to a blitz allows paper and nobody
referred to his paper and he said well
that from then on he he said he vowed
never to write a paper using the two
spinner formalism which I thought was
pretty ironic
particularly since Dirac himself I was
intriguing that a lot of people in the
early days of looking at generalizing
the Dirac equation and for high spins
and so on and there were you know Duffin
comer and what only the ones from well
they were all cause different names for
all the different spins and they were
all in coarse and smoke I remember and
Dirac wrote this header isn't it I think
earlier I'm can't remember the history
of which is which but I think earlier
this paper where he did a whole lot
using two spinners I mean direct using
two spinners what you see clearly he
knew about them as far as I was
concerned because he'd acted on them but
this was much earlier than that he had
this paper in the Royal Society
describing all the different spins with
two spinners much more much clearer much
more general simple systematic and again
nobody seemed to direct paper which is
quite curious because he'd I mean
there's a huge irony there because he
wrote his initial paper using these four
spinners and didn't realize until may be
pointed out by Vandermeer London have no
idea where he got it from you realized
that you could write all this and two
spinners and in some ways it was simpler
and really used this to generalize to
all the spins but for some curious
reason nobody or very few people seem to
refer to direct paper you know about
this famous situation where Fineman
found effectively the path integral
formalism in some paper the Dirac had
published yes in the Soviet Union now my
friends right and the firemen you know
was trembling I think and as director
you realize when you said that these two
things were analogous that there in fact
proportional and direct said are they
you had to be careful with the right
because I had a when I
written things in two spinners and I'd
written general relativity with just to
spin us in that found certain things
came out very beautifully and this thing
that everybody was worrying about
quarreling there at that time called the
Bell Robinson tensor right and you could
it dropped out of use to spin us and the
principal nail directions and all sorts
of things and the thing is you have this
equation which is the Bianchi identity
is written in two spinners and you can
see it's just the same equation that you
write for masters Fields Maxwell's
equations just the same neutrino if it
had no mass just the same they're just
the same you have it no more into the
higher the spin the more indices but
it's the same equation and you can see
it's conformally invariant all just a
part of the problem that you're gonna
get into with all these things as I
would venture to argue that even the
lowly Bianchi identity which is at the
heart of how Einstein figured out how to
do his equations yes to make sure that
effectively his vectors pointed
perpendicular to the orbits of the
symmetries that he was considering that
we don't really even understand the
things that are given to us for free
fully there's an old paper of Jerry
Kasdan I believe in which he actually
read deuces the Bianchi identity for
much more fundamental principles and the
same thing is true with the sudden
appearance of a version of the calculus
due to love each Aveda from merely
choosing rulers and protractors yeah I
really worry that we never actually
grounded these fields properly I don't
know if you're familiar I think it's
Chekhov who said that if a if a gun is
placed above the mantel place in the
first act it must be fired by scene four
well for example we have this thing
called the torsion tensor oh God that
everybody is introduced to in the first
day of romani in geometry and then they
properly are encouraged to forget about
their after never really seems to show
up in any meaningful way anyway it's
always a puzzle I know and I've never
quite made up my mind about it let's not
go into that story that yes I I don't
use it or I once wrote a paper
but to ask you just in terms of the path
forward it strikes me that what we have
learned about our physical world and
what comes up in this book is of a very
frightening nature that Einstein's
equations when you really understand
them through Hilbert sit in sight come
from the simplest possible thing we
could minimize yeah oh yes
same thing for Maxwell's equations they
spread from the electromagnetism to the
weak force into the strong force because
it was the simplest possible thing that
could be optimized I think even
Lagrangian the Lagrangian yes I'm trying
to avoid saying those words yes I know
it and then doesn't know it and then
derive yes third equation I complete
this triptych is the equation for matter
which generates all of something called
K theory which is absolutely fundamental
so I could make an excellent argument
that the three major equations to be
supplemented by one for the Higgs field
now that we found it are the simplest
and best possible equations of their
type not that we've found so far but
provably so yes I think the trouble with
simplicity arguments which I agree with
is that it's simple in one context and
what simple way to greet X it may be
yeah but nature has shown such I mean
the thing that I can't get over is that
her taste in mathematics you know i've
analogized this to raiding a jewelry
store with millions of pieces and in
under half a minute finding all the best
stuff I wanted to finish a story there
you see which I didn't quite finish it
relates to something you were saying
earlier which I at one point you see
Dirac was the same College as I was and
John's College in Cambridge and where I
was a fellow and I happened to be
sitting opposite him at one point and I
had been working on these two
many ways of looking at general
relativity and so I said that to him I
thought you know I thought something he
might be interested in goodbye would he
have opportunities he taught me about it
so so he reserved a room and I had a
little discussion with him and then I
wrote down this equation which is this
wave equation which you which represents
the bianchi identities and and I wrote
this thing down in the rack I thought he
would instantly recognize it because
it's basically the same equation that he
had in this paper with all these
different spins and he asked me I wrote
down the question is where does that
equation come from so I said it comes
from the Bianchi identities and he said
what are the Bianchi identities holy cow
and I thought well he's been writing all
these papers in general relativity in
quo you must know perfectly well the
explanation presumably is you simply
rediscovered them himself he just didn't
know them we call the Bianchi identities
I don't know it's a very curious story
yeah and this was in the form that the
derivative of the curvature in terms of
the natural derivative is equal to zero
that's yeah in vacuum say yes and you
take the the viol curvature which is all
that's left of the Riemann curvature and
you write that in spinners and it's a
spinner with four indices completely
symmetrical and then when you write the
derivative it's the derivative acting on
those four things in one contraction the
rivers got two indices and you contract
one of those and that's the equation
that's vanishes that's the equation same
as the Maxwell equations the same as
neutrino if you had one index and no
mass and it's the way I think about
these things and they're conformal
invariant just very crucial that leads
me to all sorts of ideas that I wouldn't
have thought of otherwise and it was
clearly the sort of thing Dirac would
have played with himself because his
equation all the high spin equations
although and securely in his paper he
did the massless case a different way
which I never quite understood why but
anyway it was is there clearly things
that he understood completely
and somehow maybe never connected I
don't know when it was do you did you
read his 1963 article in Scientific
American where he makes a very
interesting case against naive
application of the scientific method no
I don't near Exit in subject absolutely
in his more you should have seen that um
he makes the point in the case of
Schrodinger yeah
and he says Schrodinger would not have
been led into error if he had not been
pressed for agreement with experiment
because Schrodinger then after
publishing there was a period of time
where wasn't understood that spin
somehow entered the picture and
complicated the theoretical prediction
with its experimental verification but I
think secretly he was actually talking
about himself where he had introduced
the Dirac equation there had to be
positively and negatively charged
particles hmm and at that time the
electron and the proton were known but
the positron and the antiproton were not
and so he linked those two and
Heisenberg immediately dinged him and
said wouldn't those be of the same mass
and you're obviously making an error and
he didn't stick to his guns or have the
courage of his convictions to predict
the new particle or something man yeah
and I think that that 1963 paper from
Scientific American is direct trying to
give us a gift from Mount Olympus to say
stop with the incessant insistent on the
naive scientific method give yourself
more room to imagine more room to play
more room to be wrong I think that's
crucial thing is he he that was the
thing about Dirac he just didn't want to
be wrong now he was very worried about
saying things that were wrong and so
often he would say nothing rather than
anything so this is a big thing with him
and I think he was disturbed by yeah
you're right I mean he could have
predicted instantly I think he needed
more freedom and he didn't have it and
he tried to give that freed away being
too timid yes
what aggression yeah let me ask you a
harder question all right because we
haven't asked you any hard four
questions I'll be going
you're going to be in your nineties soon
if you were to come okay yes if you were
to point to younger people there seems
to be a failure to pass torches that
I've noticed and you don't seem to be
the sort of a person I would imagine to
have that problem who would you be
pointing to I mean an Indian being
individuals ooh
I said tricky when i teii you not to
push push anyone down but who would you
who would you build up in a who's young
and vital who might be you might say
look if anyone's got the the scent this
might be a person to look at I think I'm
not going to take you up on that one
I'll decline ya'll declined to push
further yes it's just it's not so
obvious
I mean I've certainly had people clearly
good in inspirational ways and think of
things I'd never thought of but it's bit
hard yes I don't know enough people I
think it's probably somebody I don't
know Lucy yes do you do you worry that
the glory that is the oxford school of
geometry and physics may not continue
with ours I do worry a bit about that
yes I mean there wasn't it's an
unbelievable nucleus of people you're
absolutely right it's very remarkable
and I worried that the UK doesn't value
itself enough I think that you guys are
so idiosyncratic and so weird and badly
behaved I don't know what to call it but
the UK has punched way above its weight
by tolerant tolerating and encouraging
personalities idiosyncrasies that I
think that very there is a point there
I wouldn't know how to generalize across
countries because maybe but I think I
think you were right to some degree
there is tolerance of eccentricity which
which is specifically kind of into kind
of tolerance which is specifically
English or British I should say British
I don't know I'm nervous about saying
things like that because you find
somebody springs up somewhere else yes
somebody else somebody hate you
work but quite honestly what are they
gonna do make you pay with your career I
don't think it's gonna happen yeah but I
think I think what you say about the
geometry developed in Oxford it was
pretty distinctive yes but then the
people moved out too I mean Michael went
back to Cambridge well that's what
but the Oxbridge system I mean if if I
don't have to make it so peculiar to
Oxford but you know even if I think
about like a Nigel Hitchin or Mason I
guess has been in that system yes not
very able people yeah they're very odd
Ellis no doubt about that
yes yeah but it's I mean you're asking
me to a bigger thing then but let me
just you know one final thing have you
been to the courtyard of the Simon
Centre for geometry and physics at Stony
Brook which is tiled with Penrose tiles
I've not been there I've seen
photographs of the tiling is may I
recommend a pilgrimage they have a wall
there as well yes they so-called iconic
wall which because Jim Simons made so
much money he was able to chisel into
some of them world's most important
equations and principles that you and I
probably think of as being the hallmarks
of being alive you know just contact
with these things they're actually in a
place that can be visited with a key and
I always think about in a fantastic
world unlocking that wall and seeing
whether it's in fact a gateway to
something else yeah it's a long time
since I've been there and I haven't been
there since the world over pavings
I I recommend it yeah no I'd like to do
they ask you one final question to us
that we all worry when we've gotten this
far along your road to reality if you
will that we're not going to live to see
the final chapter or completion that
this is a mystery like none other that
probably in some sense does have an
explanation and
and a kind of end is that something that
that occupies you I mean I find you
absolutely vital and sharp as a tack but
like I'm worried about this at age 54
that whatever what if I don't get a
chance to see the end is that's
something that animates so there's a
huge amount of chance involved in these
things so it's a gamble I think you know
to see a real end to all this is too
remote for that but on the other hand
you see we didn't really discuss where
Twista theory is stuck or has stuck for
40 years and where I think it's got
that's somewhat unstuck you think it
will be the answer well I'm not sure how
far it'll take us you see that's not the
question but the main problem as I saw
it in twister theory it did sort of
rather surprisingly things which worked
surprisingly well and one of these is to
construct solutions of me Einstein
equations or the Ricci flat it's four
dimensional space times which were
completely generic provided they were
anti self dual now what that means is
you've got a complex solution of
Einstein's vacuum equations which are
left-handed in some sense and I why do
we want complex solutions anyway you
know you want the real solutions well
you see I thought at one point well one
useful way of thinking about the complex
ones as these are wave functions because
wave functions are naturally complex so
I thought well this is a wave function
but it's a nonlinear wave function so I
called it the nonlinear graviton and it
seemed to me a big step forward and
understanding how quantum mechanics and
gravity fit together but it got stuck it
got stuck with what I call the googley
problem now you have to if you're not a
member of the former British Empire you
probably don't know what a googly is
it's a it's a ball mold in the game of
cricket you see in cricket unlike
baseball you'd like to spin the ball
about its axis the direction it spins
about the direction which is moving
because it bounces that's a key thing so
it bounces one way or there and to make
it spin left hand
it has a certain action with your hand
and there's a clever thing that people
do who are really good at this who can
looks as though they're using the same
action but it's very cleverly done that
the ball spins the other way and you
throw occasional one of these in it gets
the batsman completely bamboozled and
that's called the googly so using the
same action that spins the ball left
hand and you spin it right-handed so I
used that term because seem very an act
you have the frame the twisted framework
which naturally gives you the
left-handed graviton make it do the
right-handed one and I struggled and
struggled and struggled and have all
sorts of wild ideas for how to do this
and I came up with one which I was very
proud of but it needed a cosmological
constant to be zero and so I thought
there is no cosmological constant then I
had a discussion with Jerry Ostreicher
who was a very distinguished
astrophysicist and I was talking about
the observations that there seemed to be
a exponential expansion of the universe
which seemed to indicate the presence of
a positive cosmological constant so I
said well you know surely that's not
really there it's dust or something and
he looked at me I said that's not the
point there are so many things in
cosmology which works so much better if
you put this cosmological constant in so
I had to retract my view I threw out my
construction but it took me many years
to see when you have a cosmological
constant you can do something that
didn't work without it and this enables
you to have a construction which I think
solves this googley problem the trouble
is from my point of view it translates
it into algebra rather than geometry
although you even get back to geometry
by thinking of it as a connection on the
bundle so that is a geometrical thing it
is a connect connection and then you
talk about this algebra and then instead
of patching spaces together to make a
curved manifold you patch the algebra
together then they have to be non
commutative at the point that made clear
to me by Michael at T at one point and
this is the proposal you just construct
these algebras and they are connections
on bundles
and this enables you least in principle
to find a generic solution of the answer
and vacuum equations with cosmological
constant when I say find it's so you
mean it what would be called an Einstein
manifold the Ricci scalar is constant in
nonzero constant in non zero that's
right that's right exactly what people
call an Einstein's mate but this is
Lorentzian or not understood positive
definite but it's not a construction
event that you sort of write this
following me down it's you construct
this algebra and then you look for sub
algebra and the algebra and that's not
the thing I'm good at doing so but still
it needs something to collaborate oh
absolutely
and I got distracted by cosmology and
other things and I'll stay away from
that consciousness stuff it'll suck all
your time well that is a problem
actually yeah but you see other people
are doing that I'm not really doing that
I can go there get me to give lectures
on it I give the same old lecture which
I've given many many well I have to say
that if you stick with what you've what
you've done in physics and keep trying
to push that ball forward I can't
imagine a better use of your time you
are invited any time you want to come
back and return to this program this has
been an extremely heavy load for our
listeners know we don't apology
you don't apologize for that we have to
start doing something different because
people are hungry to know what does it
actually sound like to hear people
talking about where things are rather
than some spoon-fed prettified version
that's like pre-chewed as if it were
baby food I don't think they want that
anymore no I agree and I think even if
you don't understand all the things that
they get some feeling from some of the
things people are trying to do is is
really important we are as important as
the details or perhaps model part of it
is just respecting our listeners they
know that we don't know how to get this
to them in exactly the right way and so
I think we have the best listenership of
any program out there because they've
been habituated to recognize that not
every program and not every sentence is
going to make sense so Roger thank you
for coming through we'll come back any
time and
and continue the conversation about
twisters or anything else you'd like to
talk now I've really enjoyed it thank
you very much yes all right you've been
through the portal with Sir Roger
Penrose hope you've enjoyed it
please subscribe to us wherever you
listen to podcasts and if you are the
sort of person who views podcasts
navigate over to our YouTube channel
make sure that you subscribe and click
the bell so you'll be informed the next
time our next episode drops be well